We have a lot of choices
to make about our diet.
Add to that, doing
the right thing
when it comes
to preventing
and treating a
chronic disease,
fighting a virus,
or losing weight,
and suddenly our
nutrition choices
can seem almost
overwhelming.
Well, I’m here to help.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we discuss
a condition
that we might not
even know we have
until someone is brave
enough to tell us:
bad breath.
The word halitosis is derived
from the Latin and Greek terms
for abnormal or diseased breath,
though it may be
less of a medical term
and more of a marketing term,
as it was supposedly coined
by the Listerine Company.
Halitosis is commonly
referred to as bad breath,
though medical and dental
professionals often use
instead of bad breath, the
less judgy term, breath odor.
As described in the
Journal of Breath Research,
halitosis has been
classified into four types.
There is genuine halitosis,
either transient or chronic,
which is contrasted
with pseudo-halitosis,
when someone thinks
they have bad breath,
but it’s evidently all in
their head, and
halitophobia, where they start
out with genuine halitosis,
but then they treat it,
and get rid of it,
but still think they have it.
These are rare, though.
The vast majority of cases
are IOH, which stands for
intra-oral halitosis, bad breath
arising from inside the mouth,
as opposed to lungs or stomach,
and not just anywhere in
the mouth, but specifically,
in most cases, apparently coming
off the coating on the tongue.
Most people have a tongue coating,
a grayish-white deposit
on the tongue, which is the
main cause of bad breath.
Now, there are pathological
conditions like black hairy tongue,
whose symptoms may include
an unattractive appearance
of the tongue, which can
be caused by certain drugs,
but the normal tongue coating
is just a thin, slightly moist,
whitish substance across the
upper surface of the tongue
composed of sloughed
tongue cells, bacteria,
seepage from our blood supply,
and secretions from our gums
and postnasal area, like mucus
discharge from our sinuses
dripping onto the
back of our tongue.
Those with gum disease tend to
have four times as much coating,
in terms of the wet weight
scraped off the tongue
due to the migration of white
blood cells from periodontal
pus pockets onto
the tongue surface,
but even in people with
perfect dental hygiene,
food particles can get trapped
between all the little bumps
and cracks on the tongue and form
a thick bacterial biofilm coating.
If we eat the right foods, though,
our mouth may be self-cleaning.
Just the act of chewing
and swallowing foods
that actually need chewing
can cleanse off the tongue,
leaving you with just the
normal, thin layer of coating,
but fast food is engineered
to be eaten fast.
It’s soft, you can just gulp
it down and consequently,
the thickness of the tongue
coating might increase,
and that could
contribute to bad breath,
but you don’t know... until
you put it to the test.
“The effect of a chewing-intensive,
high-fiber diet on oral halitosis,”
a randomized clinical cross-
over study, in which subjects
were examined over
a period of 2.5 hours
after consumption of a
high-fiber vs. low-fiber meal
using an organoleptic
assessment of halitosis.
Although a few electronic bad-breath
detectors have appeared
on the market, organoleptic scoring
is still the ‘gold standard,’
which is just a fancy name
for when dentists or doctors
just give your breath a sniff.
Here’s the ratings they use:
no halitosis detected
even up close and personal,
or yeah, bad breath but only
up to about 4 inches away,
or out to a foot, or all the
way out to more than a yard.
We know halitosis is reduced by
eating, due to the “self-cleaning”
of the mouth while chewing
food, and it seems obvious
that foods that need to
be chewed more intensively
have a stronger self-cleaning
effect than foods
that require less chewing,
but whether this
is actually the case
had never been examined...
until now.
The participants were randomized
to a high-fiber, high-chew meal
with a whole grain roll
with jam and a raw apple,
versus a low-fiber, low-chew
white bread roll with jelly
and a cooked apple and,
the result, a significantly
lower bad breath score immediately
after the high fiber meal
and then two-and-a-half hours
later compared to the low fiber meal.
The researchers conclude that a
chewing-intensive, high-fiber meal
led to a greater
reduction of halitosis.
Most bad breath is
due to the decay
of sulfur-containing
proteins.
Here’s the story.
It has been estimated
that 90 million Americans
or approximately 30 percent
of the U.S. population
currently suffers from bad
breath on a regular basis.
And for those of you thinking “Phew,
I’m glad I’m not one of those,”
it is believed that
people with bad breath
can’t actually smell the odor
coming out of their own mouth.
Maybe this is because
they’re just used to it,
or it’s because when you
sniff, you’re breathing air
from below rather than in
front where you’re exhaling.
Either way, the mouth air of
chronic malodor sufferers
is tainted with compounds
such as hydrogen sulfide,
which produce a stream of
foul air that can be
gravely offensive to the
people in their vicinity.
The characteristic smells
in halitosis include compounds
that smell like feces, like scatole,
the rotten egg gas hydrogen sulfide,
a corpse-like aroma from
cadaverine, a sweaty feet compound,
putrescine for the smell of
decaying meat, rotten cabbage,
rotten fish, pee, apples
don’t sound so bad,
and I don’t even know what
squashed bedbugs smell like.
But, the major compounds that
contribute to oral malodor
are the VSCs, the
volatile sulfur compounds
such as hydrogen sulfide.
Bacteria in our mouth,
predominantly on our tongue,
have the capacity to produce
these odorous sulfur compounds
through putrefaction of
sulfur-containing proteins.
OK, so what can we do about it?
Many have concentrated on trying
to reduce the bacterial load
in the mouth with like
antiseptic mouthwashes,
or finding ways to trap the VSCs.
Mechanically, you can disrupt the
biofilm of bacteria on the tongue,
like with various tongue
scraping techniques,
though tongue cleaning
seems to work more through
reducing the substrates
for putrefaction,
rather than the
bacteria themselves.
OK, but if the substrates
for VSC production
are the sulfur-containing
amino-acids,
and the sulfur-containing
amino acids are derived mainly
from animal protein, meat and dairy,
what about using a
dietary approach?
The VSCs from animal protein
may actually explain why
carnivore poop smells so much
different than herbivore poop.
And indeed, limiting the
amount of consumed proteins
may significantly reduce fetor ex ore,
from the Latin meaning
stench mouth.
The reason they add fats and
alcohol is that they can both
cause relaxation of lower
esophageal sphincter.
Normally, the only time you
exhale odors from your stomach
is when you burp, because the
sphincter at the top of the stomach
prevents stuff from backing up,
but alcohol or a fat-rich diet
increases the relaxation
of that sphincter,
which further increases the
risk and severity of bad breath.
But most cases of halitosis occur
due to the decay of food residues
in the mouth by the bacteria
that decompose proteins and
amino acids and produces the
volatile sulfur compounds.
So, the treatment of oral
halitosis should involve not just
professional advice on oral
hygiene, but also diet.
Dairy proteins, for example, are
known to break down in the mouth
leading to the release of amino
acids that are rich in sulfur.
Dairy products are rich sources
of the milk protein casein,
and casein is rich in the sulfur-
containing amino acid cysteine,
which is a precursor to the
formation of the rotten egg gas
hydrogen sulfide in the oral cavity.
In fact, that’s how you can
test people for bad breath.
Cysteine challenge testing:
just have people
swish their mouth with it.
When cysteine is degraded,
not only do you get
the hydrogen sulﬁde, which
comprises a large part
of the bad breath bouquet,
but you get sulfhydryl anions
that favor the growth of the
very bacteria within the mouth
responsible for the protein
putrefaction that’s central
to the production of oral
malodor in the first place
and to the development
of gum disease.
So, it’s not just a one-two
punch, but a triple threat.
Bad breath isn’t just
some aesthetic issue;
these volatile sulfur compounds
can be toxic to the gums,
even at extremely low concentrations.
Hydrogen sulfide reacts
with collagen and can alter
the protein structure, thereby
rendering your gums and jaw
more susceptible to destruction.
Then you can develop
these pockets of putrid pus
that can lead to more halitosis.
The periodontal pockets
are the second main source
of the volatile sulfur compounds.
Even people with mild periodontitis
may have twice the risk
of reporting bad breath.
Finally, let me touch
on the role diet has
in so-called extra-oral halitosis,
bad breath that doesn’t
originate in the mouth.
There are lots of
drugs that can do it,
including dietary
supplements like fish oil,
but there’s another way people
can smell fishy: trimethylamine.
Trimethylaminuria is
one the largest causes
for undiagnosed body odor.
It’s when you can’t sufficiently
metabolize a malodorous compound
called trimethylamine,
which is formed in your gut
when you eat lots of choline.
The textbook presentation
is urine, breath, sweat,
and reproductive fluids smelling
like rotten or decaying fish,
but what many doctors don’t
realize is that the fish odor
presentation may only occur in
like 10 percent of individuals
who have this predisposition.
Yes, at high concentrations,
trimethylamine has a foul,
rotten fish odor, but
at low concentrations,
it can just give you kind of a
unpleasant garbage-like breath.
And because there are many
foods that are rich in choline,
like the fact that there are
eggs found in so many foods,
you may not make the
connection between your diet
and your body odor, but you
can always try cutting out foods
like egg yolks for a few weeks
and see if you smell any better.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a vital, timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my latest book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
Or go to your local public
library for that matter.
For recipes, check out
my new “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books
goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.